Welcome back!
In the previous step, we solved the simple problem in a structured approach, and in this step we would
want to focus on how to solve it in a functional approach.
What I'll do is, I'll copy this file and paste it down here. I'll rename it to, FP01Functional.
Let's open up FP01Functional and that's where we'll try and solve this problem.
Let's start with renaming the method.
Right click, Refactor, Rename, and I would want to rename this to
printAllNumbersInList, in a Functional approach. That's what we would want to do.
So, we'd want to print all the numbers in a Functional approach.
We have a list of numbers passed in.
Now, how do we do this in a Functional approach?
One of the important things to remember is, in the functional approach, we will focus on, 'What to do?'
Before we can focus on what to do,
what we'd need to do is, we'd need to convert the list of numbers into a stream of numbers.
What does that mean?
You can see, that the list of numbers is this. You'd want to convert this into a stream.
So, I would want to convert it into a sequence of elements.
I would want to first get 12, then get 9, then get 13, then get 4,
and so on and so forth.
So, we would want to convert whatever we have, into a stream of elements.
How do we convert a list into a stream?
The way we can do that is by; let's comment out this piece of code, Ctrl slash or Command slash,
and followed by Ctrl Shift F or Command Shift F to format it. Cool! That's commented out.
We'd want to create a stream for numbers. So, numbers.stream.
As you can see in the Java doc, it says, "Returns a sequential Stream with this collection as its source."
So, we're taking a list and converting it into a stream of numbers.
So, we are converting it into individual numbers, which come one after the other;
a sequence of numbers: 12, 9, 13, 4. Once I have a stream of numbers,
what I can do is to specify, what to do with each one of them.
So when I get 12, what needs to be done? When I get 9, what needs to be done?
What do we want to do with each one of them?
We'd want to do a System.out.println(number) right?
So what we'll do is, we'll create a simple method, which accepts a parameter and prints it out.
So, let's create a simple method in here.
So, I call this private static void.
I'll just call this, print and let's send
in a int number to it.
What this will do is, it will just do a System.out.println(number).
So, it just prints a single number, that's it.
Nothing more, nothing less.
Now, what do we want to do over here?
numbers.stream() for each number. For each of these numbers, for 12, for 9, for 13, for 4,
we would want to call the print method.
How do we call the print method from here,
for each of the numbers? The way we can do that is by
saying, forEach, and you can define;
I would want to call the print method. Now, over here,
typically what we'd do, we'll say print of 5.
Alright! So, typically what would happen?
This code would be immediately executed.
We don't want the method to be immediately called. What we would want
to do is to define, what needs to be done.
We need to define the behavior, when we get a number of 12.
To define the behavior, we use something called a method reference.
How do you put a method reference in?
What we want to do is, for each element we'd want to call this print method.
How do we say that? The way we can say that is by using, the name of the class, colon,
colon, followed by the name of the method.
So, you can see that this is a static method and I'm using the class name colon, colon the name of the
static method. And what I'm telling it is, hey! take the numbers, convert in into a stream,
and for each element; for 12 do a print, for 9 do a print.
That's basically, what we are specifying in here.
Now, I think we have got almost everything covered. So let's do Right click, Run As, Java Application.
Aha! The output does not really change.
You can see that, everything is being printed out in a sequence.
Let's end this step by reviewing quickly, what's happening with this code.
What we are doing is, we are converting the numbers list into a stream.
So instead of getting a list like this, what we'll get is, a stream of elements like this.
And what we are specifying is, for each of these elements which are coming out, what we would want to
do is, to call the print method which is present in the current class.
And the syntax which we are using in here is, colon, colon.
This is the syntax of something called a Method Reference.
What we are saying in here is, for each element, this method needs to be called.
So, for each of the numbers coming up, what would happen is, this print method would get executed
and that's how we were seeing all the elements that are printed.
I'm sure there are a lot of questions about this specific approach.
Hold onto them, and I'll see you in the next step.