Welcome back.
In the last two steps, we implemented a simple problem in a structured approach and the functional approach
and you might be thinking now that the functional approach is much more complex than this structured
approach.
And that's true with the implementation that we have right now.
Let's see what we can do to simplify the implementation that we have.
So, let's first remove all this stuff that we have in here.
So, let's actually remove the earlier code that we have inside the functional method.
I'm using Ctrl D or command D to remove a line and now let's see the need for this specific print method.
What we are doing in here is, we would want to call FP Functional colon colon print.
We would want to call a static method in this specific class.
And what happens is, for each element in this stream, this static method is called with that element.
So, this stream contains a list of numbers.
So, first 12 is sent to this method,
next nine is sent to this method,
next 13 is sent to this method and we saw everything is printed out to the console.
That's cool.
Now, instead of doing this, you can actually replace this piece of code by directly specifying System.out
in here.
So, System.out and what is this static method? println.
So, System.out contains a static method called println and that's a easier way of doing it. Instead
of creating a new method called print,
what we can do is, directly call System.out::println.
And now, this method is no longer needed.
So, let's comment it out.
Now, you can see that this piece of code is a little more simpler than the structured approach.
Why do I call it simpler?
Because in this Structured approach, we had to focus on how to loop the numbers and then print them. In
the Functional approach,
on the other hand, we get a list of elements and we define what to do with each one of them.
So, all that we needed to do is to say for each element in this stream, do this. Now,
let's try and make the example that we have little bit more complex.
What I want to do is, I would want to go to the FP Structured class and what I would want to do is to
print only the even numbers.
I don't want to print all the numbers in the list but I only want to print the even numbers in the list.
So, instead of saying print all numbers in the list,
I only want to say print even numbers in the list structured.
How do we change this code to print even numbers in the list?
Think about it.
Typically, what we do is, we would add the logic in here. So, we'll say, if this is even, only then print
the number out, right?
So, let's do that.
So, if even,
how can I check that the number is even? If(number), we can divide
by two. So number%2==0.
So, we are dividing by two and checking the remainder. So, number%2 divides the number by two and checks
the remainder.
If it's zero,  then what do we want to do? Yes, we would want to print the number out.
So, let's format this out.
And now, if I call this, so printEvenNumbersInListStructured, I can copy and paste this in but then
I would be repeating the list.
I don't really want to do that.
So, what we'll do is, let's extract this list to a local variable. So, right-click, List factor, extract to
a local variable and local variable that I would want to create is numbers and over here, what we want
to do is, we would want to print all the even numbers in the list. Right.
So, that's basically what we want to do.
So we are using the Structured approach and let's run as Java Application. What would happen? Cool. Only the even
numbers are getting printed.
Now how do we do the same thing in a Functional approach?
How do I do that in a FP01functional class? Let's see how to do that right now.
So, I'll copy the existing method. As usual,
I'll call this printEvenNumbersInListFunctional and over here,
what we want to do is, we'd want to only look at the numbers which are even. So how do I add additional logic
in here. I can add a Filter in here. I'll say, only allow even numbers.
How can I add a Filter? The way I can do that is by saying .filter.
Now, how do I decide if something is even? Let's create a static method for it, for now. I'll call this private
static, this return whether it's even or not. So I'll say boolean, private static boolean isEven
and let's pass the number to it.
So, int number and this would return.
What does it return?
number%2
is equal to, is equal to zero.
This is simple logic. Right?
All that it does is, it divides the number by two, checks the remainder, and if the remainder is zero, it returns a
'true' back.
Otherwise it returns a 'false' back.
What do you want to do is, we would want to call this method on each of these numbers.
And only if it is true, we'd want to print the number. So you'd want to do a forEach,
only for the numbers
where isEven is returning true.
How do we do that in the Functional approach?
The way we can do that is by creating a filter.
So I said .filter and over here, I can say isEven.
And because this is a static method, the way we can define that is by using a method reference FP01
Functional colon
colon isEven. The important thing in the method reference is that we are not really calling it, we are
not really calling it. We are just saying, okay, this is a method to be called.
We are declaring that this is a method to be called on each of the numbers and if it returns true back,
only then go to the next line of code.
So, let's move this comment out, down to this side and let's now execute this. Let's quickly create a local
variable for this list as well, numbers. And what we want to do is, copy this and we would want to print
even numbers in the list.
Let's comment this out.
Let's quickly run this and see what would happen.
Do we get only even numbers?
Yup.
That's cool.
Now, we saw that we were able to print all the even numbers in the list.
Once again, you can see the fact that once we have a stream of numbers, all that we needed to do was add
a check.
So, for each number, do this check. If that check is true, then you can actually go ahead and print the
number out.
Now, again you might be thinking that this method is a little bit more complex than this structured approach
because we needed to use a method called isEven.
How would it be, if I can actually directly define the entire
isEven method in here.
Instead of actually creating a separate method, having a return value, having the parameters defined,
having the body, having the return and all that, can we do it in a simpler way and directly define the
method in here.
Let's look at that in the subsequent step. Until then,
bye, bye.