Welcome back!
In the previous step, we solved the problem for printing even numbers in a Functional approach.
However, we needed to create a separate method, isEven.
We saw that the logic for this method is very very simple, and we had to do a lot of ceremony.
We had to add in a lot of detail to define the method and call it from here.
Is there a simpler way of doing it?
Let's look at it right now.
The simpler way of defining this specific thing is called a Lambda Expression.
So, what I'll do is, I'll comment this and I'll say .filter and over here,
what do we want to do is, we would want to define a Lambda Expression. So, what is a Lambda Expression?
A Lambda Expression is nothing but a simpler way of defining another method.
So, Lambda Expression is nothing but a method.
Very very simple.
However, in the Lambda Expression, you'd use a simpler syntax for creating this method.
What does this method accept as a parameter?
Let's start with that.
So, this method accepts number as the parameter, right?
So, what do we want to do is, we'd want to take number as the parameter and we would want to check.
What do we want to check?
We'd want to check, if number mod 2 == 0.
So, we would want to take a number and we would want to check, if
number mod 2 == 0, and return it back.
And this is something of a special kind of a syntax related to Lambda Expression.
It's hyphen, followed by greater than symbol.
So, this is almost like an arrow symbol.
So, what we are saying in here is, take the number in. So, take the number and check if number mod 2 == 0
and return it back. By default, in Lambda Expressions, if you just have
one statement present, it will return that value back.
So, what would happen in here?
It takes the number and returns the value of  number mod 2 == 0.
How do I use it in our code?
I just need to copy this and put it in between parenthesis of filter.
So, what we are defending in here is, saying number, for each number,
for each number, what do we want to do? Check, if number mod 2 == 0.
If number mod 2 == 0, then return True back.
Otherwise, return False back.
Let's see what would happen. Cool!
No change in output, but you can see that now the code is much much more simpler,
because I don't really need to worry about this method anymore.
So, this method can be commented out and all logic that we have right now;
I'll move this line of code a little below.
So, the logic that we have right now is to convert the list of numbers into a stream
and for each of the numbers execute the filter.
So, is this condition True?
If the condition is True, then go ahead and do the print. As you can see in here, with functional programming,
we are focusing on the, 'What to do?'.
For each element, what to check? You are checking that the number is even.
For each element, what to do if the condition is True.
We would want to print it out. The thing which we learned in this specific step is something called a
Lambda Expression.
So, Lambda Expression, as we discussed, is a simplified representation of the method.
So over here, we had a method called isEven,
which was returning number mod 2 == 0.
We just used the same logic in here, in much more simpler syntax.
If this is the first Lambda Expression that you wrote, the syntax might look a little weird, little new,
and all that. Don't worry, we will be writing a number of Lambda Expressions in the
subsequent steps and you'd really get comfortable with them.
Let's quickly review the important concepts that we have learned until now.
Number one, with functional programming,
we focus on what to do.
We convert the numbers into a stream and for each element in that stream,
we specify what needs to be done.
A stream is nothing but a sequence of elements.
For each element, we would want to call the isEven method in here
and we use a method reference to define that in here.
The other approach to defining what needs to be done
with each number, is something called a Lambda Expression. With a Lambda Expression,
you can define the entire code directly in here. With a method reference,
we are actually referring to a method which is defined somewhere else.
However, with the Lambda Expression, we are actually defining the complete logic of the method right here.
I hope you are having a lot of fun and I'm sure a lot of these concepts are new
and as I said earlier, FP, functional programming, is actually a paradigm shift.
So, it will take some time for you to get adjusted to this.
So, follow along and keep watching the next steps
and I'm sure you'll be learning a lot about functional programming.
I'll see you in the next step.
Until then bye-bye.