Welcome back.
In the previous steps, we looked at a few functional programming basics. And in this step, let's do a few
exercises to try and consolidate our knowledge.
Let's start off with a simple exercise.
It's to print only the odd numbers from the list.
So just like we have the method printEvenNumbersInListFunctional, create another method called
printOddNumbersInListFunctional.
The second exercise is to print all the courses individually. Instead of using a list of integers,
what we are doing in here is, creating a list of String courses
and we are creating a number of courses in here.
So, we would want to actually take this list and print each course individually on its own line by using
Functional programming approaches.
The third exercise is to print courses that contain the word Spring. So, print only those courses which
contain Spring in them.
The fourth exercise is to print courses whose name have at least four letters in them.
You can pause the video in here and try these as an exercise. Let's get started.
I'll go to our FP01Functional, copy it, and I'll call this FP01Exercises. And over here, what I would
want to do is to remove all the commented code out. So I'll remove all this stuff which is not really needed.
And the only method that I'm interested in is printEvenNumbersInListFunctional.
Cool. We have that ready.
What do you want to do is rename this, right click, refactor rename, print even numbers in list.
Actually, we'd want to printOddNumbersInList. Right? How do I check whether something is odd? number
% 2 == 1.
So, if a number leaves a remainder of one when divided by two,
it's a odd number.
All right. So, that's basically the logic that we are using to print odd numbers.
You can also say number%2 !=0.
Even this code would work.
So is equal to, is equal to one or not equal to zero.
Both of these logics should work.
So, I'll run this as a Java Application.
Cool.
Nine, 13, 15. So only the odd numbers which are present in here are being printed out.
The second exercise was to print all courses individually.
This should be simple. Right?
So, what I'll do is, instead of creating separate methods for that, we'll actually directly write the code for it
in here. So, I'll create a list of courses.
So, if you look at these courses, they are quite a number in here.
So Spring, Spring Boot, API, Microservices, AWS, PCF, Azure, Docker, and Kubernetes. You can create
a list like this containing your favorite set of courses.
And what we'd want to do now is, we'd want to print all of them.
So, with Functional programming, the first thing that we would do is we'll convert it into a stream. And
for each element inside the stream,
what do we want to do? First is, we would want to just print out them. So, System.out::println.
Cool. Isn't it easy?
Let's comment the earlier one. So, I'll comment
these two lines of code and let's execute just this line of code right now.
Let's run it as Java Application and see all the courses that are being printed.
So that's Exercise 2
done.
Now, the Exercise 3 was to print only those courses that contain the word Spring.
How do we do that?
I'll copy this, paste it down,
comment this out, and over here what we want to do is to add a filter.
And what should be the filter?
For every course,
only filter the course that contains the sequence Spring.
Right?
That's what we'd want to do. Let's now try and run this, run as Java Application. Cool. Only
Spring and Spring Boot are now being printed.
Now, you can pause the video in here and try the last exercise,
if you have not tried it yet. What's the last exercise? It's to print courses whose name have at least four letters.
So, courses.stream() .filter. I would want to allow only those courses which have at least four characters. So, I
would want to eliminate AWS and PCF. How do I do that? Over here I can define course and course dot. Oops!
Actually, I should use course in here;
so it should not be courses. course, course.length is greater than or equal to four.
Now, let's run this. Awesome.
Only six courses are being printed out. So, you can see that now we are able to filter the courses that
we would want to have. In this quick step,
we looked at a few exercises to implement the concepts that we have learned in the previous steps.
I'm sure you're having a lot of fun and I'll see you in the next step.
Until then bye, bye.