Welcome back.
In this step, let's try and add a little bit more complexity into our Functionality.
What we'd want to do is, we would want to print squares of numbers.
Until now, we have been printing the numbers as is.
How about printing the squares of each of these numbers?
How do we do that?
Let's look at that.
So, I'll copy this method out. I'll say printSquaresofEvenNumbers.
So let's print squares only of the even numbers in the list.
So, we have a stream, we are allowing only the even numbers to go through, and then printing them.
However, over here, we would want to actually print the squares of the numbers.
How do I do that? The way I can do that is by doing something called a mapping.
So, what we'd want to do is, we would want to map each of the element, we would want to take each of the
element and map it to the square of the element.
So, we'd want to calculate the square of the each element and then print the square of the element.
So, how do we do the mapping? The way we can do the mapping is by saying map
and you can define the mapper function in here,
the mapper lambda expression in here. The mapper lambda expression is, take x or take any number,
and once you have the number, what we would want to do with the number? We would want to actually multiply
it by itself.
So, number * number.
So, this expression is called a mapping expression, where we are mapping a number to number into a number.
The result of this is at the end of it. The number would be multiplied by itself.
So, we'll calculate the square of the number.
And after that, the square would be printed.
Let's try and run this. Oops.
We have not changed the call in here.
So, we don't want to print even numbers in the list. We would want to print the squares of all numbers.
So, let's do this, printSquaresOfEvenNumbersInListFunctional and let's run this. Run Java application
and you can see that squares of all the numbers are being printed out.
Now, you can pause the video in here and try and do a few more things as an exercise. The two exercises
are Exercise 5 and Exercise 6.
Exercise 5 is to print the cubes of only the odd numbers. A cube is nothing, but a number multiplied
by itself three times.
So, three cube is equal to three into three into three, which is 27. Exercise 6 is to print the
number of characters in each course name.
So, I would want to print six characters.
Here it would be 11 characters,
here it would be three. So, instead of printing the course itself,
I would want to print the number of characters in that.
Now, you can pause the video in here and try those two things as an exercise.
Let's go ahead and solve them.
So, what we would want to do in the exercise is, I'm in FP01Exercises.java.
And what we'd want to do is, printCubesOfOddNumbers. And the way I can do that is very simple, right?
I would want to map each element, each number which is present in there.
What do I want to do with it?
I'd want to multiply by itself three times, number * number * number.
That's it.
Let's take this and let's use the list of numbers which we have already created and call this in here by
passing in numbers.
Let's see what would be happening. Run Java Application.
The code is a little messy.
So you can see that only for the odd numbers, the cubes are being printed.
Don't really worry about what's printed after this. This is a result from the courses stuff which is after
this.
So, that's cool.
We are now able to do the cubes of odd numbers.
The next exercise was to actually print the length of these courses.
How do we print the length of these courses? Let's look at it right now. So what do we want to do?
courses.stream().
We don't really want to filter anything. For all the courses, what do we want to do?
We'd want to print the length. So, we can map each of the courses. So each of the course,
what do we want to map it to?
We'd want to map it to course.length(). So, map
course to course.length() .forEach(System.out::println). Isn't it cool?
Let's not really worry about this.
Let's comment this out.
And let's run this code.
You can see, over here, that this is printing the lengths of each one of this. Just to be really really
clear,
what we'll do is, we'll append the course with the space and the course.length().
So, what we are doing in here is, course + " "
+ course.length. Let's run this.
You can see that it's printing Spring 6, Spring Boot 11 characters,
API is 3 characters, and so on and so forth.
As we discussed before, it's very very important to get your hands dirty with functional programming.
We are used to doing the traditional approach for a number of years
and there is a lot of unlearning to do before we would get comfortable with functional programming.
I hope you're having a lot of fun and I'll see you in the next step. Until then,
bye bye.