Welcome back.
Before we move into the next section, let's review some of the important concepts that we have learned
in this specific section.
The first thing that we have learnt is, in Functional programming we focus on specifying what to do.
First of all, we converted the List to a stream.
So, this is a sequence of elements
and for each element what should be done. Allow it,
if it's only an odd number. Print the element out to the console. Do a cube of the number.
So, for each element in this stream, we specified what needs to be done with it.
We used numbers.stream() to convert a list into a stream and then we looked at a couple of important
methods on the stream.
We looked at filter which allows us to specify a condition. Only if
that condition is matched, then the element would go further.
Otherwise, this element would be filtered out.
So, if I have a list of numbers and I would want to allow only even numbers to go through or odd numbers
to go through, then I can define a filter specifying what is the condition that needs to be checked on
the number. forEach is used to consume an element.
You take an element and print it.
That's what this specific thing helps us to do.
We use map to map one value to another value.
So over here, we took the number and we did a cube of it, number * number * number.
The other things which we looked at were Lambda Expressions.
You can see that filter, over here, uses a lambda expression. The map over here, uses another lambda expression.
Over here, we are using a lambda expression to take a course and append the course.length() to it.
We learnt that lambda expression is nothing but a simplified representation of a method.
So, this lambda expression over here which takes a number and returns if it's even, is similar to the method
which we wrote in here. It takes a parameter called number and it returns if that specific number is
even. So, instead of writing this much amount of code, we would write a simple lambda expression.
We also looked at Method References. Until now, we have used method references to call static methods.
println is a static method on System.out.
So, we are saying, on the element call System.out.println element. And we use the method reference
to specify that. We also created method references using custom static methods.
We created a method called isEven and we use the class name
: : isEven to call it. If you have not started doing the hands-on yet, I would recommend you to get
your hands dirty and write as many functional programs as possible.
I'll see you in the next section.
Until then, bye bye.