Welcome back.
In this section on reference types, we would discuss about what are reference types, how are they stored
in memory, and how are they different from primitive types. In the previous sections,
we created a number of classes and this is how we create instances, right.
We used a new jupiter
here is a reference variable, Planet here is a reference type, and over here when we created a int variable,
i is a primitive variable and int is a primitive type.
We will discuss about all of these concepts and we will go one level deeper.
We will talk about how the reference variables and primitive variables are stored in memory,
what happens behind these screens when you assign a value to a primitive variable or you try to assign
one value to another.
We will also talk about how they are initialized.
We will also look at a few reference types in Java.
These are predefined in the sense that Java provides them for you.
So, they come free for you with Java.
These are string.
There are a set of classes called wrapper classes and also we will look at a few date time stuff.
So, we'll look at LocalDate and LocalDateTime.
I'll see you in the first video where we would start discussing more about reference types and variables.
Until then, bye-bye