Welcome back.
In this video, we would be talking about reference types and reference variables.
We will understand how reference variables are stored in memory and also compare and contrast them with
the primitive variables.
Okay, let's get started.
What is a reference type, right? So, any class that you create is a reference type. So, here the class Planet
is a reference type.
There are also pre-defined classes in Java.
String is one of the pre-defined classes in Java.
This is a reference type.
We looked at BigDecimal earlier and BigDecimal is a reference type. Instances of the classes that we
create,
here we are creating an instance of the Planet, new Planet and we are storing it into jupiter;
jupiter is a reference variable.
Why is this concept called reference variable important
and how are they different from a primitive variable?
Here, i is a primitive variable.
So, here I am saying jupiter is a reference variable.
Let's now start with discussion about how the reference variables are stored in memory and how is this
new instance stored in memory.
Let's create another class.
I'll call this class, Animal.
Let's say, in this Animal class we have a int id.
So, for each Animal let's say, we are assigning an id and to make it easier for ourselves, I'll create a
constructor.
If you remember the syntax of the constructor, it's very simple, right. So, the name of the class followed
by the open bracket followed by what arguments I would want to pass in, int id
and over here I can do this.id = id and close bracket and sorry, close brace and close
brace.
That's it. So,
we have an Animal created in here.
This Animal can have a id value, right.
So, I'm not going to create getters and setters and make this private for now.
Let's just keep it very simple.
Now this class called Animal has a field called id,
right.
So. now how do I create instances of the Animal class? I can create it
Anima dog = new Animal
and pass the parameter. Let's say
the id I am assigning to this dog is 12, right.
I can create cat
and assign it a value of 15.
This is kind of the code that we typically write.
Nothing fancy in here. It's very simple code.
What is happening here is what we are really interested in.
Now, let's bring up a fancy spreadsheet to understand what's happening in the background,
right. Whenever you create a new object, whenever you create a new object, these things are stored in something
called a Heap.
When a Java program runs, it has some memory and there are two kinds of memory, one is a Stack and the
other one is a Heap. All new objects are created on the heap. This heap is kind of a common place which
is shared by the entire Java program.
So, in this heap all your objects are stored.  So, new Animal(12), let's say is stored in here. I'll say Animal
12.
This is not exactly what will be stored in the memory. But let's use that as a reference. So, Animal12
will be created on the heap. Heap consists of a number of locations,
right.
So, I just gave some names to this location.
Let's not worry about the size of this location and all that kind of stuff because that would become
very complex.
Let's just give a name to these locations and use them as the reference.
So, let's say Animal12 is stored in location 1A and Animal15 is stored in 1C. It can be randomly
assigned anywhere and can be stored anywhere. But I'm just assuming that it's stored in a specific location
on the heap.
Now, when we create primitive variables, they're always created on the stack.
So, when I create a local variable in a method, it's always created in a stack.
So, this is the way it would be stored. So, the variable name is i,
the value is 5.
That's how they are stored.
So, when I create a primitive variable, all that would be stored is a variable name
i, with a value 5.
When I create a reference variable, as we discussed earlier, this is stored. Where is this stored?
This is stored on the heap.
Now, where is this stored?
The dog is actually stored on the stack somewhere.
So, dog is stored. The variable name is dog
and what would be the value, dog is refering to what? new Animal(12)
So, what is the location, Animal(12)?
It's at 1A. So, the value which would be stored in here is the memory location.
So, in the dog, what is actually stored is a reference of the memory location, where the actual dog
object is stored. That's the most important concept and that's why it's called a reference variable.
It's called a reference variable, dog is called a reference variable, because does it have the value of
the dog?
Nope. It refers to the memory location of where the dog object or the animal object exists in memory.
Similarly, the other variable, cat.
So, now cat. How does the cat get created?
What's is the id?
15, right. So, 15,
1C.
So, this is how reference variables are stored in memory. The actual object is created on the heap
and what would be stored in here is a reference to the location where the object is stored in memory.
This distinction is the reason why a difference between primitive and reference variables is very very
important. In the next video,
let's dig a step deeper and look at what would happen when I assign a primitive variable to another
and what would happen when I assign a reference variable to another and also look at a wide variety
of other operations.
Until then, bye bye.