Welcome back.
In this video, let's look at a variety of puzzles related to the reference variables.
We'll try and understand in depth about the reference variables, different concepts like equality of
reference variables, initialization of reference variables, and assigning reference variables.
Let's look at all of them in this video.
Let's get started.
Let's say I'm just saying Animal nothing and creating this.
What would be the value which is assigned to nothing?
As you can see, it's null and how is this stored? The way nothing is stored is, because we did not create
anything,
nothing is created
and in here the value which is stored is null.
That's basically means it does not have a memory location present. So, it's empty.
It's kind of empty. Null refers to empty.
So, null here means, it's not referring to anything. It's a reference variable but as of now nothing is
referring to nothing.
I would want to store the reference to cat in nothing.
What would happen?
I'll say nothing = cat.
Now, you can see that, you can see the memory location here is same as this,
right.
When I do nothing = cat,
what happens is, where is cat stored?
1C, that gets copied into, into the memory location of nothing.
So, basically we are not doing anything with the objects. So, when we are saying nothing = cat,
what is happening is the, from the cat reference variable, the location of where the cat object is stored
that is getting copied into nothing.
That's basically what is happening in here.
So, if I say nothing.id = 10, what would be the value of cat.id?
What do you think would be the value of cat.id?
It's also 10, because the way it would work is nothing.id,
nothing is referring to which object? nothing
is referring to 1C.
So, what would happen? Here,
the object at 1C would be changed.
So, I am changing the value of it to 10.
So, what would happen? This value becomes 10. The value inside the object becomes 10.
So, now the value which is pointed to by cat is also referring to the same thing.
So, it has a value of 10.
This is very important concept to understand, right.
When we copy reference variables, when I say nothing = cat, what gets copied is the memory location
where the cat is stored. That gets copied into nothing.
Let's say, now I would say dog = nothing. What would happen? If I say dog = nothing,
1C gets copied into 1A. I'll not do that.
What I'll do is I'll say nothing = dog.
What will happen now?
Nothing = dog, right.
So, what would happen?
The memory location of dog gets stored into nothing.
Now, if I say nothing.id, whose id is printed? nothing.id would print the id of the dog, 1A 12,
right. So let's print. It's
printing 12. So, it's very important to understand what's happening in the background, so that you'd
be able to exactly know what's happening in here.
However, in the case of primitive variables, what would happen? If I say int j = i,
what would happen?
j gets a value of 5, right. So, j is created with a value of 5
and even if I change the value of j,
the only thing which gets modified is j.
So, with the case of primitive variables what you are storing here is the value.
So, if I type in i, i would still have a value of 5.
However, with the case of reference variables, what we are storing is the memory location. When I copy
a reference variable, what gets copied is the reference to the memory location where the actual object
is getting stored.
Now, let's say i == j, what would happen? i == j
is a false, because i has a different value as j.
Now, let's say I copy the value of j = 5,
right. So, i and j now have same values.
So, if I say i == j, what would happen?
It has a value of true, right. Now,
let's take the case of the reference variables. Let's try and recreate the same objects again.
So, let's say Animal dog = new Animal of, dog is referring to 1A, 12, right? So, let's create
exactly the same way
and cat, earlier was referrring to
let's say 1C 10,
right. So, let's say it's 10, cat is referring to here.
We need to create nothing. Instead of nothing,
I'll call it ref, just a ref.
So, I'll say Animal ref and what I'll do in here is, I'll assign the reference to cat. What ref stores
is the reference to the cat. So,
1C.
I'll also create another dog2. Let's say it also has the same value for the id, right.
So, we are creating another dog2 which will have Animal12.
So, let's say, it's stored here, Animal12 and we are calling this dog2
and this is
at location 1E,
right. So,
very simple. Now,
over here, let's now try the == operator,
right.
So, cat == dog,
what do you think would be the output? false,
because they are not referring to the same object,
right. That's cool. Now,
cat == ref,
Yep.
They return a true because they're pointing to the exactly the same object, right.
So, this is the same object they're referring to.
However, the interesting thing is dog == dog2.
What do you think will be the output? It says false. Even though they have the same values, that does
not matter.
What is important is the objects they are referring to. The object they're referring to are different.
So, here we are referring to a different object
and here we are referring to a different object. On the heap,
we are referring to two different objects.
So, here 1A and 1E. Even though the values are the same but their locations on the heap are different,
they are distinct objects on the heap.
So, the important thing to understand is when we are comparing reference variables using ==,
what we are just comparing is, if they're referring to the same object.
If they have references of two different objects, it does not matter even if the values are the same.
The answer would be false.
The important thing to understand here is the == operator for a primitive variables
compares the values. But for reference variables, compares if they are referring to the same object.
If they are not referring to the same object, it would return false.
In this video, we discussed how a reference variable is stored in memory,
what would happen when I assign a reference variable to another,
and also how do you compare equality of reference variables.
We learnt that a reference variable, if you do not assign it a value, then it has a value of null
and we also learnt that the reference variable points to a location of memory where the actual object
is stored and when we compare reference objects what we are comparing is if they are pointing to the
same object,
dog = cat only if they are pointing to the same memory location.
cat = ref only if they are pointing to the same memory location and when we are assigning
a reference variable to another, what gets copied is the reference of where it is stored in memory.
The object does not get copied. All that gets copied is the reference.
So, if I say dog = ref, this 1C gets copied into this location.
That's all. The actual object is not really affected.
We'll talk about these concepts much more when we talk about garbage collection in a future section.
Until then, bye bye.