Welcome back.
In the previous sections and also the little bit of this section until now, we have created classes, created
methods in them, created instances of these classes called objects, and we invoked methods on these objects.
We also learnt about primitive data types versus the reference types. From this video on,
we would start exploring the inbuilt reference types in Java. In the next set of videos, we would be starting
to look at String, Wrapper classes, and also a few reference types to refer to it. In this video,
let's start with the basics of the String class.
Let's start with a simple question.
We created a number of literals like this. With in double quotes, we said this is representing text.
One interesting thing to note about this strings is, actually this is a instance of a class called String.
How can I prove that?
All that you need to do is to say, "Test".length( ). Oops!, I am a little too early.
I just need to login into JShell first.
So, let's log into JShell before I would be able to execute the command.
Now I can execute "Test".length( ). I am in JShell right now and it's printing 4. This Test string has four
characters,
length is a method and Test is an instance, instance of what class? In Java, text is represented by a class
called String.
If I want to store str as a Test, this is how we would do that.
So, String str = "Test" creates an instance of the Test and stores the reference of it in
str. String
is very very special.
All the other objects you would need to do something like a new BigDecimal, right.
So, when we did BigDecimal, we said BigDecimal bd = new BigDecimal of let's say 1.0.
So, we needed to use a constructor to create it.
However with String, you don't really need to use a constructor. Even though if you would want str
=
you can do new String("Test").
You can do that. But that's not really necessary.
All that you need to do is String str = "Test" and that's more than sufficient. String
is a special class in Java.
This Test is an instance of the class, String.
This is called a String literal.
We looked at the basic method which is present in here, length.
We'll start looking at a few other methods which are present in the String class to retrieve the details
about a specific string, right. So, in String,
the index starts with 0.
So, this is 0,
this is 1, e is 1, s is 2, and t is 3.
So, if you want to get a specific character,
so let's say I would want to get the first character of a string,
the way I would need to do that is by saying str.charAt(0).
The important thing is, the index starts with 0. So, 0, 1, 2, and 3.
So, let's quickly check another one str.charAt(2). It returns s. 0 is T, 1, and 2 is s.
str.CharAt(3),
that's the last character.
Let's say I don't want to retrive one character but I would want to retrieve a substring from this particular
string.
Let's create a more bigger string. So, biggerString =
"This is a lot of text". So, let's say I have this text in here
and from this I would want to get the substring starting from 'is', right.
So, I would want to get all the characters starting from here.
How can I do that?
Doing that is called a Substring. Substring methods accepts the index of this character.
So, we would need to pass in the index of this character
and it would be able to print the rest of the strings.
Let's do,
biggerString. , I would want to do it from
i. So, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, and 5,
biggerString.substring(5). So, it's printing "is a lot of text", right.
So, that's how you do a substring. I'm trying to get a part of the string. Here
we are specifying the start of the string. But you can also specify start and end also. So, I'm specifying 5
as the start and I can specify okay, this is 5,
I would want to get up to 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. So, let's say, I would want to get up to t, t is at
index 12. So, if you want to get up to character with index 12, then you need to enter 13.
So, the important thing to understand is this side is inclusive,
this is exclusive.
So, this index is not really included.
So, the character at index 13 will not be part of the substring.
So, the character at index 13, if we do it,
so if I do str.charAt(13), you would see that it returns a space back.
Oops! I should have actually done biggerString.charAt(13). So, biggerString.charAt(13),
it prints a space out.
So, this is the space which is present at character 13 and that is not included in the string, because
this is exclusive.
So, starting from the character at index 5 to 12. So, it's when I pass in a 13, only the character
upto index 12 would be included in the substring.
I will recommend you to try and play around with these things charAt, substring and see what you can
find.
One interesting aspect is, if you try and give a index out of the range of the string, so let's say the
string is length 5 and you give an index of 15 then it would throw a StringIndexOutOfBoundsException.
Exceptions are Java's way of telling you; Okay buddy,
as a programmer you are doing something wrong, I'm throwing you an exception.
How can I get the 10th character in a string of length 5? That's wrong.
That's an exception.
The same kind of exception would happen with charAt, if you do something invalid and the same thing
would happen with substring
also. So, if I say, charAt(456), 456 is an invalid index. So, it would throw you a IndexOutOfBoundsException.
Okay. In this video, what we looked at is number one, we looked at the fact that every string literal is
an instance of a class.
This is the only type of literal which is a instance of a specific class
and also we discussed the fact that string is a special type, in the sense that we did not really need
to do a new string to create an instance of the string. All that you need to do is str1 =
"SomeString" and Java would automatically create an object for you.
This is something unique to String and also we looked at and also we looked at a few important methods
substring and charAt. At the end of this video, we were introduced to a simple concept called exceptions
which we will discuss a lot more in a separate section on exceptions.
I'll leave this video with an exercise.
So, let's say I have a string, right. So, let's say I have a very simple string, String someString =
"This is a lot of text
again". What I would want to do is, write some code in here which would print individual characters on
separate lines. So, the output should be 't' on one line, 'h' on next line, 'i' on next line, 's' on next
line, and so on, and so forth.
We'll discuss the solution in the next video.
Until then,
bye bye.