Welcome back.
In this video, we'll talk about some more methods on the String class.
Before we discuss about the methods on the String class, let's pick up the exercise from the previous
video.
We have a string and we would want to print each of the individual characters on separate lines, right.
If you are able to do it already, that's cool.
If you are not, I'll give you a hint right now.
So, how do I find out the length of the string? someString.length( ),
right.
This gives you that it's 27. The index of this string would run from 0 to 26, length minus 1.
I would want to print individual characters at each of those locations.
Okay.
Did an idea
strike you? Try and pause the video and try and work it out.
Okay.
If it did not,
then another clue. How do I find out what's the specific character at a specific location? someString.
charAt(5).
This gives me the character at index 5 which is i, right. So, 0 is this. So, starting with that, if you
start counting, this will be 5.
So, it gives me a charAt(5).
So, now does this strike you? Do you think you can solve this on yourself? Try and
pause the video and try it.
Okay.
Now the solution is very simple, right. So,
i= 0; i<someString.length( ). So I am running a loop from, i is 0 to one less than the
length.
So, from 0 to 26, in this specific example and i++ and all that we would need to do
is System.out.println and what should we do?
What should we print?
someString.charAt(i). Isn't this cool?
Okay.
You can see all the characters printed on individual lines.
This is a lot of text again.
So, all that we did is very simple. We created a loop starting from 0.
I mean from 0 to length-1 and we incremented i and we printed the character at that specific location.
Isn't that cool?
Okay. Now, let's move on to what we want to discuss in this specific video.
Let's take the same string from the previous example
and now I would want to find out if a specific string is present in this.
So, I would want to see if a word called 'lot' is present in this specific string.
How do I do that? The way I can do that is by using a someString.indexOf, indexOf and pass in the
string. What does it return? It returns the starting index of 'l'.
So, it returns 10.
So, if I do a someString.charAt(10), it would return me 'l'.
So, this is returning the index of 'l'.
So, it's searching for 'lot' in the string and returning the index of the first character of the substring.
Now, let's say I would want to search for a character.
So, I'm not searching for a string, but a character.
So, let's say I am searching for 'i'.
How can I do that?
charAt, the same name, this is an overloaded method which accepts a character parameter and this returns
the index of this. Because that's the first 'i'. Oops!
Actually, I should use indexOf, right.
So, it's not charAt.
I should use indexOf('i').
So, it returns 2. So, indexOf is the same method.
It's an overloaded method and we would use indexOf to find the index of a string, a substring as well
as a specific character.
So, 'i' in this string is at location, index 2.
Now, you might want to find out what is the index of the last 'i' which is present in here.
You can do that too very easily using lastIndexOf, lastIndexOf and this returns 25.
One thing you should be careful about is the Camel casing. So, indexOf, O is caps,
CharAt, A is caps, indexOf, lastIndexOf, I and O are caps.
So, be careful about the Camel casing of these methods.
The names should exactly match. You cannot use a different case. That applies to anything in Java.
It's case sensitive except for whatever is going in your literal characters or literal strings.
The other functions in String help you to check a few things on the String.
So, let's say I want to find out if this string contains a word called 'again'.
How can I do that?
I can do, use indexOf, but the other option is to do someString.contain( ).
So, if I want to present, I want to check whether a text is present, so I just need to say "text" and you can
see that it returns true.
I would want to find out if this string starts with a specific string.
I can say someString.startsWith
("This"). This would return true. The same thing if I give some other thing, it would return a false back. The
same similar method is endsWith( ). So, endsWith,
let's say, some garbage, it returns false.
If I give the right string, so endsWith("in"): yes,
endsWith("ain"):
yes,
endsWith("again"):
yes.
If I do something wrong,
false.
So, you can use this to find out if a string endsWith or startsWith a specific substring.
The last utility method is to check if a string is empty. So, you can check if a string is empty by using
the someString.empty( ).
Actually it is, isEmpty( ).
Okay. So, someString.IsEmpty( ) returns
if it's empty or not.
So, any string which has some content is not empty.
However, this string is empty.
So, that's the isEmpty( ) method.
The last useful method inside String to check the content is Equal.
So, you want to find out whether two strings are equal, then you can say, "true".equals("true").
So, this is string, so or you can say some "value" is equals some ("value"). So, you can also use a string variable
on the other side. So, I can say string str = "value" and I can say, Oops! string, i said str str.
It should have been string str = "value" and I should say str.equals
("value").
It would return true.
So, if I want to compare if two strings are equal, I can use either equals or if I want to compare them
without worrying about the case,
so for example, this value has a capital thing.
If I do this, it would return false.
Because this is caps and this is small, but if you want to ignore the fact that, that you can say
equalsIgnoreCase("VAlue") and it returns true. So, it ignores the case. It does a kind of an uppercase on both
of these and check whether they're same.
So, in this video, we looked at the exercise from the previous video, we wrote a simple loop upto the
length of the string, and we printed all the characters by using charAt.
After that we looked at a variety of methods in the string API to find out specific things from your
string, whether it startsWith specific thing, endsWith something, whether it has a specific substring present
in it using contains, and how do you compare a string with another string.
We talked about equals and equalsIgnoreCase methods.
One important thing is we have not really tried to modify the content of the string until now.
In the next video, we would start trying to modify the value of a specific string.
Until then, bye bye.