Welcome back.
You would have heard a number of times that string is immutable.
That means the value of string cannot be changed.
Is that really true?
Yep, it is true.
So, in this video, let's explore that a little bit further and look at other ways of getting a modified
string from a specific string.
Okay. Now, let's type in a simple piece of code String str =  "in28Minutes" and let's say
I'm concatenating str.concat("is awesome").
Okay, some self-praise there. But I guess you can ignore that.
So, what we are doing is str, str.concat("is awesome").
Concat is a function to concat a string content of that specific string with another string.
So, here it's
we said "in28Minutes is awesome". Because there is no space either at the end or here.
It's becoming like a single word.
I would try and print the content of str.
What do you think the content of str would be?
Aha!
It's "in28minutes".
So, the thing is, the content of str has not really changed.
So, even though I am calling str.concat("is awesome),
the str remains the same.
What it does is, it returns another string. So, String anotherString = str.concat, this
time,
let's be very careful.
I'll give a space and say " is awesome". Now, what would happen?
You can see that anotherString is assigned this value
and if I print str, it's "in28minutes".
So, whenever I'm trying to modify a value of a string, what we're doing is not really modifying that
specific string.
So, if I'm doing str.concat for a specific string, what we are doing is, we'll create a new
string and return it back. The original string remains unaffected. So, str remains "in28minutes".
We are creating anotherString, with the value of the new concatenation.
So, let's say now, I'd say String, instead of calling another string, I'll say string2 = anotherString.
I feel that there is, let's say, I would want to append
a "."(dot).
I'm saying string2 = anotherString.concat.
What happens is a new string is created, string2 with
"in28Minutes is awesome" with a dot.
But if you type in str, it remains "in28Minutes".
If you type in anotherString, it remains this
and if I type in string2, the value is with a dot. This behavior of a String class is called immutability.
Once an instance of a String class is created with a specific value,
you will never be able to change the value of that specific variable.
This "in28Minutes" will always remain "in28Minutes".
If you try and execute a method on it, it would create a new string. But the original value remains as
it is. It remains "in28Minutes".
Okay.
Now that we discussed this in great detail, let's focus on the other methods that are present in String
class to get modified values from the String class.
Let's start with a simple strings, "in28Minutes is awesome.".
Let's assign that.
So, now we have a new string, "in28Minutes is awesome."
and let's say I would want to make it all uppercase.
How do I do that?
You can have a function called toUpperCase, "in 28Minutes is awesome." and similar to that
guess, what is the function to do a lowercase?
Yeah, you're right.
It's lowercase.
Let's say there is some space at the end of a string and the start of a string.
Let's say there's a string called str2,
there is some space at the start and some space at the end
and I would want to remove that.
How do I do that? str2.trim( ).
It removes spaces at the start of a string and at the end of the string. In this video, what we looked
at is the fact that, String class is immutable. Any instance of a String class, once it's created in memory,
the content of that cannot be changed.
We looked at all the different operations which are present in String like toUppercase, toLowercase,
trim, and concatenate which would help us to get a new string with a modified value of an existing string.
I'll see you in the next video where we would be talking about a few more utility methods in the String class.
Until then, bye bye.