Welcome back.
In this video, let's look at a few more utility methods which are present in the String class as well as
we would discuss something very important called concatenation operator.
Let's start with the concatenation operator which is +, right. So, we looked at 1 + 2, what would be
the value? It would return 3. The same thing if I do strings,
what would be the output? Think about it.
It's 12.
So, it actually just concatenates 1 with 2 and returns it back. Let's say one of these is a string
and the other one is number.
Will the value change? Nope.
It is "1" + 2.
So, if the number is 23, let's say, it's 123.
However, just 1 + 23 would return 24.
So, if there is a string in one of the operands, then what would happen? Is it becomes concatenation,
+ behaves as if this is a concatenation. So, 1 is concatenated to 23.
So, 123. However, there are no strings. 1 + 23 is returning back,
24. If I have 1 + 2+ "3", what would be the result? Right,
it's printing 33.
Let's try a different thing.
Let's say I don't do this, but I would do this. 123,
that's interesting,
right.
So, why is this happening? The way expressions are evaluated in Java are left to right. So, left starts with
1.
So, 1 + 2 is 3.
So, this is performed as an integer operation. So, any normal, any operation between two integers is a integer.
So, 1 + 2 will return 3.
However, once there is 3, the result of this is 3, once we have the result,
now, it's 3 + string 3, then it becomes concatenation. So, that's why it is 33.
In this case, let's start from the left, 1 + 2 is 1, is a string, 2 is an integer.
So, the result is a string.
So, 1 + 2  becomes concatenation, 12 and 12 is a string again. To that, we are appending 3.
So, 123.
So, the rules of concatenation are very simple. It executes from left to right
and if you see two integers as part of the operation, it would be addition. If you see one string and
one integer, it's concatenation.
If it's both strings, then it's concatenation as well.
Okay.
That's how we would do a lot of our printing, right. So, whenever we did System.out.println,
we were using +,
right.
So, if I have a integer variable, let's say int
i = 20.
I can do System.out.println
"Value is" and we said + 20,
right.
So, this is how we did it.
"Value is 20" is printed.
This is because of the concatenation operator: string and int. String and int, it becomes concatenation.
So, if I'm doing + 20, what would be the result?
Value is 2020;
it's just concatenation. Try a puzzle, right. So,
if you want now, I would want to print 40.
What can I do?
What can I do is, put it in brackets.
Once you'd put it something in brackets, the brackets get priority.
So,
Value is 40.
Let's look at a few other utility methods which are present in the String class.
So, this is a static method which is present in String.
This is join method. Lot of scenarios, you would want to append comma to a list of numbers, right. So,
if I want a string with 2, 3, 4, so I can do something of this kind.
This returns, the first character is what character you want to join with, and rest is a list of strings
that you would want to append.
So, 2, 3, 4.
So, if I just have lesser number values, let's say 35 or 'A', let's say this is 'B', and this is 'C'. It prints A, B, C
and if there is only one, it just prints 'A'. If there are two, it would start appending a ','. So, this is a
very useful utility thing when you would want to separate the different values inside a string using
a ','.
The last utility method is to replace.
So, let's say, in this string, I would want to replace a specific character. So, I can say replace character "a"
with character "z". What would be the output? "zbcd" or you can say, even replace a string, right. So, replace
"ab" with "xyz". So, it becomes "xyzcd".
That's cool right.
So, what we are doing is, it's trying to explore the string APIs. One of the important things is trying to
discover and understand the APIs might become little boring after a while.
There are so many different methods that are present, that it's impossible to remember all of them.
I think the way you can look at it is, try to understand what are the possibilities that are there.
What are the possible operations that are present?
You don't really need to remember all the method names that are present.
If you are unable to find out what is the right method to do something, you can just say,
let's say, I have a string variable, right str = 25 or some text, right.
I can just say str. and it would show you all the different operations which are present on that
specific string. So, you can try and research that method further and see if that matches your needs
and also there would be a few static methods which are present. So, you can type the class name and press
'.' and press tab and that would print all the static methods that are present in there.
We have not really discussed every method which is present in there because that means we'll be spending
the entire course just discussing the string API.
But the idea was to capture the essentials and give them to you and at any other point if you would
want to find out whether such kind of feature is there, you can just type in str. or string.
and find out what are the other options which are present. The other way you can do to explore the API
is to type in Java doc and type in the class you would want to explore and say which version. Since I would
want to look at the string class in Java 9,
I'd want to look at the Java doc for it.
You can take this and this would show the entire documentation for the String class.
So, as you can see in here, it says, the String class represents character strings. All string literals in
Java programs such as "abc" are implemented as instances of this class
and if you look at it, it says Strings are constants, their values cannot be changed after they're created,
right.
We'll talk about StringBuffers later. But the idea is,  you can actually look at the documentation in
here.
Let's say you would want to explore a specific method,
what it does, concat what it does,
you can just click the method and look at examples down there as well.
So, one of the things I would recommend you to do is, try and look at the APIs and try and understand the
different methods which are present.
It's impossible to remember all the APIs.
So, try and get an awareness of what can be done and whenever the need arises,
you go and search the documentation to find the right methods. Until the next video, bye-bye.