Welcome back.
In this quick video, we would want to look at a couple of alternatives for the String class.
One of the problems with the String class is String is immutable.
So, as soon as I create a string like this, let's say I am doing "123" + "123" +"1234"+
"123456". Think about how many strings we are creating.
So, this creates the entire concatenated string.
So, when we are doing this operation, what we are doing is, we are creating individual string instances
for 1, 2, 3, and 4. So, four values in here. Because the concatenation runs from left to right, first
these two are concatenated and 123 + 123 becomes
123123.
So, this is the 5th instance
and after that another instance concatenating all these three and sixth instance and then a seventh
instance.
So, just to do a simple concatenation, we had to create seven instances of this string, right. The first
four are definitely needed because those are values, but there are three additional instances of objects
that are being created
and that's a very costly operation. Creating objects
is very very costly.
If this is the case, if it's four simple strings,
but imagine the case when I have to append 200 strings. How many useless objects would be created? To avoid
that, Java provides another class called StringBuffer.
So, StringBuffer is another class in Java which you can use to create strings.
However StringBuffer is not as easy to use as a String, right. So,
if it was a String, I can just say this. Oops!
That's not allowed with a StringBuffer. You have to actually use new StringBuffer
("TEst")
The important thing is StringBuffer is mutable.
That means if I do a sb. let's say, append and say append("123") and I leave a space in here.
What would happen? sb
value also gets changed. So, sb new have, sb has the new value, right. Now,
so the value inside the string buffer is changing.
So, it's actually saying "TEst 123". sb.setCharAt, let's say I would want to replace this character
with a 'e'. So, I can say charAt, index is
(1,'e').
Now, if I do sb, it would show "TEst 123" because we have replaced this character.
One thing you would notice that with StringBuffer is that, we are actually changing the value inside
the StringBuffer .
So, that's an important thing.
So, in StringBuffer you can actually change the values. Whenever you do a lot of concatenations,
it's preferred that you'd use a StringBuffer.
There is another class which is offered in Java which is called StringBuilder. StringBuilder is
very very similar to StringBuffer. But it's offered in the later versions of Java because StringBuffer is
a synchronised class.
So, what does that mean?
That means, that StringBuffer is a class which is ready for multithreading. But if you are ready for
multithreading, it means that there is a penalty which is imposed on you.
That means when you're running in a single-threaded scenarios where you don't really need all the complexities
around multithreading, StringBuffer might get really slow and in those kind of situations, you can use
StringBuilder.
We'd talk about multithreading and all that kind of stuff a little later in this course in a separate
section.
But for now, you can think that if you don't really worry about multithreading, then you can use a String
Builder.
So, instead of a StringBuffer, you can use a StringBuilder. So, I can say StringBuilder sb =
new StringBuilder with your string.
If you further explore the APIs of StringBuffer and String Builder, you would see that there are
variations in the methods that they offer and things like that.
But effectively, the thing which you'd need to remember is this. If you're concatenating a lot of strings
and creating a lot of instances of strings, then it's recommended to go for the alternatives, either the
StringBuilder or the StringBuffer. If you don't worry about multithreading, then you would really be
advised to go with the StringBuilder class. If you want your code to be thread-safe, then you'd go for
the StringBuffer
class. We will discuss more about multithreading when we encounter that in a subsequent section.
In this video, we discussed the alternatives to String, StringBuilder, and StringBuffer and things
like that.
I'll see you in the next video.
Until then, bye bye.