Welcome back.
In this video, we would start discussing about wrapper classes. We will try and understand what are wrapper
classes and also we'd discuss about why do we need wrapper classes.
What are wrapper classes?
So, we know that there are a lot of primitive variable types that we have already discussed about, right.
So, boolean, byte, char, double, float,
int is the one which we used frequently, long, and short.
The thing is, in Java,
there are corresponding classes for each of these primitive types. So, these classes are called wrapper
classes, because they are like a wrapper around this value.
So, if I take int, the wrapper class is Integer. All the other ones are exactly the same names, so boolean,
Boolean except for char as well. So, char is Character.
So, the wrapper class for char is Character, for int is Integer and all the others is just the same
name with a capital alphabet starting off.
This is how your wrapper classes are now.
The question might be, okay, if I have primitive values why do I really need a wrapper class?
Why do I need a wrapper class?
The thing about wrapper classes is, they offer you a lot of options, additional options.
Let's say I would want to create a boolean value from a string or I would want to create a integer value
from a string.
You can do that using wrapper classes.
The other things that wrapper class provides are a number of utility methods.
So, let's say, I have a float and I would want the integer value of that specific float.
I can use a intValue( ) method.
Let's say I want to convert a string which is in binary format. So, binary is 0 and 1s.
So, let's say, I have a string in the binary format and I would want to convert it into integer representation.
There are a lot of utility methods like this which are offered by the wrapper classes. And also, wrapper
classes
allow you to store primitive values into a collection.
We will talk about collections, a little later. If you want to add anything to a collection,
it must be an object and wrapper classes provide the objects around these primitives. Don't really worry
if you are not able to understand these methods, we would discuss them in detail a little later.
The idea behind this video was to introduce you to the concept of wrapper classes and understand why
do we need wrapper classes.
We'll discuss about each of these wrapper classes and some of the important methods which are present
in them in the next video.
Until then, bye bye.