Welcome back.
In this video, let's discuss how do you create wrapper classes. Creating wrapper classes is
very very simple, right.
So, just like you create an int i = 5.
Let's say I'd want to create an integer with similar things. I'll say Integer integer =
new Integer(5). Now,
that's how we would create it, right. So, now a
integer value is created with a value, 5.
Now, let's say I'm creating another Integer, integer1 with 5.
So, now integer and integer1 are having the same value, 5.
This is one way of creating integers. The other way of creating integer values is by using something
called valueOf. There is a static method in each of the wrapper classes called valueOf
and I can say valueOf(5) and I can say, integer1 = valueOf.
So, these are the two ways you can create wrapper classes; directly use the constructors or you can use
the valueOf methods which are present.
These are static methods which are present in each of the wrapper classes.
If you look at the integers constructor, it can also accept string values,
"5234".
So, you can do that as well. So, you can pass in a string and create an integer based on that.
You might be asking, if I have two ways of creating wrapper classes, which one should I use?
Which one of these is a better way to create wrapper classes? To understand that further,
let's dig in.
So, integer,
let's say, I'm creating i1 = new Integer(5).
Let's create i2 also using new Integer(5). Same value, I'm creating two integers.
I would use Integer.valueOf( ), right now. So, I'll call this
i3 and do Integer.valueOf(5). Now, let's do an
i4 with the same thing. Now, I'll do i1 == i2.
If you remember this,
this is a reference type.
This is a reference variable. For reference variables, == does not compare the value.
It compares where they are stored in memory.
So, i1 = i2, they have the same value. But it's false.
But if I do i3 = i4,
Aha,
it returns true.
One of the important things is just like String class, all the wrapper classes are also immutable.
So, that means once a value is assigned to them, you cannot change it.
Over here,
what is happening is, for i1, a new integer variable is getting created and i2, another integer variable
with the same value is getting created.
What Integer.valueOf( ) does is okay,
why do I need to create another instance of the same value? It would check and re-use if there is an existing
object of the integer with the same value.
If it finds another object with the same value, it would try and re-use and it would return the same
thing back.
That's okay because the value of that object will not change.
Integer is immutable.
You cannot change the value of it.
So, having two reference variables pointing to the same object is not a problem at all.
What we would recommend is to use Integer.valueOf( ) or the valueOf methods to create any of the
wrappers, because valueOf tries and reuses whatever objects are already created.
So, it does not create a new object every time. When you use a new,
you are creating a new object every time.
However, Integer.valueOf( ) does not do that.
It would try and reuse existing objects which are present inside the heap. Similar to the integer, there are
float functions which accept a double, which accepts a float, and also a string. So, you can use all this
constructors, as well as you have a Character constructor which accepts a character, and a Boolean constructor
which accepts a boolean as well as Strings.
So, for a String, it accepts True, capital true, capital False.
I mean, you can use true in any case. So, it would be able to use that and create a value for it. So,
for this, the value is true. For this also, the value is true and for this, the value is false
and if you try and do something else, some string, then it would create a value of False.
So, these are the different things which are present.
You can also use the same kind of stuff with the valueOf on each of these wrapper classes.
I'll recommend you to try all that stuff as an exercise. Creating those wrapper classes will not be any
different from creating the Integer wrapper class that is present in here. In this video,
we looked at how to create wrapper classes using a constructor and also valueOf. The same kind of wrapper
classes for Integer exist
also for all the other wrapper classes. In the next video, we will learn about more ways that wrapper
classes can help you.
Until then, bye bye.