Welcome back.
In this video, we would talk about one of the new features in Java 5, which is called Auto Boxing, which
allows you to write code with primitive values, but compiler does a lot of work for you and converts
them into wrappers.
And also, we would look at a few constants that are defined inside these wrapper classes.
Let's get started with this concept called Auto Boxing.
So, I said the way you would create a wrapper class is by saying Integer seven = Integer.valueOf(7)
,
right.
So, this is the way
we were creating wrapper classes until now.
But this is too long a way because you can do this as well.
What is happening in here is Auto Boxing.
What happens is when you do this, Java in the background would do this, Integer.valueOf(7) and create
an instance of it and put the reference of it in seven.
This feature in Java is called Auto boxing.
The important thing is Auto Boxing uses Integer.valueOf
and we know that Integer.valueOf uses all the things again.
So, if I create something like sevenAgain and = 7, because these are using Integer.valueOf,
you would see that these are referring to the same variable. So, if I say seven == sevenAgain,
you would see that the value is true. Auto Boxing uses Integer.valueOf. The existing objects,
the existing wrapper class objects are reused and you can see that the same reference is present in both
seven and sevenAgain. Auto Boxing is a very important thing. At later stage, we would also look at how do we use
Auto Boxing to add primitive values to a collection. Features like this are called syntactic sugar,
right.
Who wants to type in the extra characters?
I'm a lazy guy
and so I guess, would be you.
So, we don't really want to type in a lot of code and that's where features like Auto Boxing would really
help.
Having looked at all these features on the wrapper classes, the last thing which we want to talk about wrapper
classes is the different constants, which are defined on each of these wrapper classes.
So, if you look at the wrapper classes, they have a MAX_VALUE.
It indicates what max value can a integer hold.
They also have a MIN_VALUE; what is the minimum value that an integer can hold. If you want to find the
size of an integer,
you can do that as well and you can get the size in bytes as well. So, size is in bits.
So, this is 32 bits and this is 4 bytes. These kind of constants are present on all the wrapper classes.
In this video and the previous sets of videos, we looked at wrapper classes, we looked at the fact that
they're immutable, we looked at the fact that there are a wide variety of features that these wrapper
classes offer, and we looked at the fact that we should always use valueOf instead of using new with
the wrapper classes. We also looked at the various constants that are present in this wrapper class like
MAX_VALUE, MIN_VALUE, SIZE, and BYTES which would help us get more information about what kind of values
you can store into these wrapper classes.
I'll see you in the next video where we would start discussing about a brand new topic.
Until then, bye bye.