Until then, bye bye.
Welcome back.
Until now, we looked at various kinds of data types, right.
We looked at integers, floating point values,
we looked at booleans,
we looked at characters, we looked at strings.
The only data type which is missing until now is dates, right.
So, in this video, we would start exploring dates. Before Java 8,
one of the constant problems with Java APIs is the implementation of date. They did not really have
a good date API
and that's where a new implementation for dates is provided in Java 8.
The new implementation was based on something called Joda Framework. So, this Joda was a very famous
alternative to the Java API for dates and Java 8 brought in some of the important concepts from Joda
into the Java API itself.
So, we'll use that API, we will use the API which is introduced in Java 8 to discuss about dates in this
specific video.
Java 8 brings in three most important classes. So, LocalDate, LocalDateTime, and LocalTime.
These are the three classes which makes playing with date and time very easy.
So, what is LocalDate, what is LocalDateTime, and what is LocalTime?
So, date can hold a date. So, 10th October 2017, 15th December 2015. So, LocalDate can hold a date. LocalTime
on the other hand can hold just the time. So, it can hold the time saying 23:25.
That stands for 11:25 p.m or it can say 1:25, so 1:25 a.m. LocalDateTime
can store both the date and the time. So, it can store things like, okay, 11:25 p.m on 10th December
of 1985.
Let's start exploring the API with LocalDate.
If I say, LocalDate now = LocalDate, there's a method called now( ).
This would fail.
Now, why is this failing?
Think about it.
What could be the reasons, why it's failing?
LocalDate is in a package called Java.time. One of the important things is, JShell provides a few default
imports.
So, if I do a /imports, it would show the default imports.
That's the reason why, we were able to use the BigDecimal class,
the String class without having a problem, because it was in the packages which are in the default imports.
However, this package, java.time.LocalDate, is not in the default imports. So, we would need to import it in. So, I will say
java.time.LocalDate. LocalDate
is now imported.
Now I'll execute the same statement and now, you would see that the LocalDate instance is now created.
You can see the value of it being printed in here.
It's saying 2018-02-01.
The same thing,
if I want to do with LocalDateTime, what would happen?
Think about it. LocalDateTime.now( ): error. Because we have to import that as well.
So, LocalDateTime.
The other option is to import everything together. So,
*,
right.
So, now I would be able to do a LocalDateTime.now( ).
So, the difference between LocateDate and LocalDateTime, as you can see in here, is LocalDateTime represents
both date and time whereas LocalDate only represents the date
and if I do a LocalTime, it represents only the time and you can see the different details that are
stored in here. In the next video,
we will start exploring all these three APIs a lot more.
Until then, bye bye.