In this video,
let's get started with the LocalDate. LocalDate today = LocalDate.
now( ). Make sure that you have the import in place because if you don't have the import, so you need to
have the java.time.* in your imports.
So, if you restart JShell, you need to again import it in. So, import java.time.*.
That's when you would be able to do LocalDate
today = LocalDate.now( )
and you can see that it's printing the
today's date. So, 2018-02-01.
One of the important things about the LocalDate, is offers a lot of ways of getting information about
this date.
So, once we have created today, now I can get a lot of information about today.
Let's look at those methods now. So, let's say I would want to get the year.
I can say getYear( ) and print 2018.
I want to getDayOfWeek( ). It's printing Thursday.
So it says,
it says, today is a Thursday
and if I want DayOfMonth( ), so that prints 1, because today is the first day of February.
So, today's date is 1st February
and if I want to print DayOfYear( ), it prints 32 because today is the 32nd day of the year.
So, you can see that there are a number of methods which help you get information about the specific
date.
So, I am able to get
which day of the year, which day of the month,
which day of the week, and all that kind of information just by creating a simple variable using the
now( ) static method.
You can also get details about the month.
It's February
and if you want the number, you can get, getMonthValue which would return 2.
So, those are all the important methods in the API which would help you get information about the specific
date.
Now you might sometimes want to get some more generic information, right whether the year is a leap year,
how many days are there in that specific year, how many days are there in that specific month.
The cool thing is, Java 8 DateTime API provides you all that stuff very easily.
So, if I want to find out isLeapYear( ). All that I need to do is today.isLeapYear( ). Nope, it's false.
So, I am right now in 2018 which is not really a leap year, right. So, it returns false. I can find more information
about it. So, you can say today.lengthOfYear( ).
So, how many days are there in the current year? 365.
I can say lengthOfMonth( ), 28.
So, these methods help you get meta information about the year or the month we are in:
how many days are there in the month,
how many days are there in the year, whether it's a leap year and things like that. And also, the date API provides
ways to add number of days or number of months or number of years to your date. So,
I would want to find out what is the date after 100 days. So, I can say today.plusDays(100).
What's the date after 100 days?
It says 2018-05-12,
right.
So, it says 12th May 2018 is plus 100 days from now.
You can also do plusMonths( ). So, plusMonths(100). So, 100 months from now is 1st of June, June
2026 or you can even do plusYears( ),
100 years from now.
Okay.
I will not be alive then, so 2118.
These are all the methods you can use to add days, or months, or years to your date and you can also have
subtraction, right.
So, today.minusYears(100) or minusMonths( ) and
minusDays( ).
So, these are all the things to change the date. So, you can add the number of days, add number of months,
or a specific number of years to the date.
One of the important things that you'd need to remember is all these do not change today value. LocalDate
Time
class is immutable.
So, what we are doing in here is, we are creating new variables. The
today itself does not get affected.
So, today minusYears(100) would be a new variable.
So, I can say LocalDateTime, actually it's LocalDate.
LocalDate hundredYearsBefore
= today.minusYears(100).
The value of today on the other hand would still remain today.
It creates a new variable called hundredYearsBefore with the value.
So, this is immutable class again. All the methods would create new instances with the new value. Until
now,
in this video, we have looked at a wide variety of things, right.
So, we looked at how to get specific information: which day of the year, which month, which year, and all that kind
of stuff.
We also looked at getting generic information; leap year, is it a leap year,
what is,
what is the number of days in the current year.
what is the number of days in current month.
And, we also looked at different operations to add  number of days, months, years, and subtract years, and
stuff like that.
The interesting thing to note is that very similar APIs exist on the LocalDateTime class as well.
So, on LocalDateTime class,
if I create a instance of it right now, DateTime.now( ), there are very similar methods present.
However, in addition to the usual ones,
so let's say I want to do a plus, the LocalDateTime not only allows plusDays, plusMonths, plusYears,
and plusWeeks, but it also allows plusSeconds, plusHours, and plusMinutes.
So, all that I had to do was now.plus( ) and press tab and it would show all the options present. So,
LocalDateTime provides all the options that are present for the LocalDate plus it allows you options
to play with hours, minutes, and seconds, and nanoseconds as well. So, over here what you are seeing in here
is nanoseconds.
So, that's basically what the LocalDateTime provides. So, similar to adding, you would also be able to get
different information, right. So, now.get( ), you would be able to get minute, you'd be able to
get second,
you'll be able to get nano,
and you'd be able to get the hour as well.
I'd recommend you to try and play around with the LocalDateTime API on your own and try and find out more
things about it. In this video,
we looked at few of the important methods that are present on the LocalDate class.
We looked at how to play with it.
We also looked at a few methods which are present in the LocalDateTime.
In the next video, we will explore a few more things about the LocalDate and the LocalDateTime classes.
Until then, bye bye.