Welcome back.
In this video, let's look at a few more utility methods present in the LocalDate class which help you to
compare dates as well as set a specific value to a date.
So, until now we created a LocalDate object using LocalDate.now( ), right. So,
what we did was LocalDate today = LocalDate.now( ).
But there are other methods which are there which can be used to create specific dates. So, instead of
today,
let's say, I would want to hard code the date and get the details about yesterday. Yesterday was 31st,
31st Jan.
So, for now, let's hardcode, I could have got 31st by subtracting one day from here.
Let's hardcode the values now.
So, there's a method called, of( ).
I can say 2018 and I can say 01, 31. Oops!
I got something wrong.
Okay, this is how it would be.
So, yesterday, oops, I got the spelling wrong as well.
Okay.
Yesterday is 2018-01-31.
So, this is one method which can set, help you to set a specific value.
So, of( ) is a specific method in LocalDate which will help you to create a LocalDate instance, specifying
the specific year, month, and day.
So, now, today has this
and yesterday has this.
That's cool, right.
There are methods which are present which would help you to set a specific year on this date.
So, I would want to find out the same day, but with a different year. I can say today.withYear,
I can say 2016, for example.
So, it becomes 2016, the same day, first February in 2016 and you can also do today.with, a specific
day of the month.
So, let's say I would want to have the date as of 20th day of this month.
So, it would become 20 February 2018.
You can do the same thing with the month as well. So, you can say with today.withMonth( ) and say
I would want to be in the third month. The interesting method which is present in here is, today.with
DayOftheYear( ).
You can say I would want the same year,
but with a specific day. So, 120th day of the year. So, it would return me 04-30.
So, 30th April is the 120th day of 2018.
So, what we are looking at in here is, we started off with looking at different way of creating the Local
Date with a specific date, month, and year and we are looking at, once you are having a specific date,
how do you modify it with a specific attribute.
So, I would want to modify the year, or a month, or a day, or you would want to use the current year with a
specific day of the year.
So, these are all the options which are present in LocalDate to be able to do all these things.
One of the typical things that we would always do with dates is, we would want to compare.
Once you have two days, you'd want to compare whether they are before each other or after each other
and there are methods to do that as well. So, you can do today.isBefore(yesterday).
Is that true?
false. today.isAfter(yesterday)
true.
So, this is to allow us to compare dates. So, isBefore( ) and isAfter( ) are two awesome methods to compare
dates as well.
Whatever dates that we discussed on the LocalDate
class are also present on the LocalDateTime and the
LocalTime class as well. And, in LocalDateTime,
you'd also be able to do things like withHour, withMinute, withSecond, and things like that. So, you
can get specific things to manipulate hours, minutes, and seconds as well.
I'd leave that as an exercise for you to explore the LocalDateTime and the LocalTime APIs. In
this and the previous set of videos, we explored a wide variety of things related to the LocalDate, Local
DateTime, and the LocalTime classes.
We tried to play around with the dates and we tried to explore the API further.
As I said before, exploring APIs is not really a fun thing.
It's a huge number of methods that you'd need to remember.
So, try and remember, what are the operations you can do and if you want specific details or about a specific
thing that you would want to do,
you can always a look at the Java docs of the API. All that you need to do is, if you want to search for
LocalDateTime,
I would just need to say  java doc LocalDateTime and Java 9 and you'd be able to get the API and you can read
it and try and find out more about a specific class.
The most important thing for you is to remember that there is a specific class existing and probably
you can do a few things of this kind with that specific class.
Once you know that, once you are aware of that, you can locate the specific details from the documentation
of the API.
I will see you in the next video.