Welcome back.
In this video, let's explore how to explore different APIs using Eclipse.
So, let's say I would want to find out everything there is to find out about the List interface.
How do I do that?
You can type in Control Shift T or Command Shift T and choose the List class. Type in List and you can
choose the List class inside Java SE 9.0.1
So, let's make sure I'm using the right one. So,
this is the interface that I would want to choose, Java util. Over here,
once you go into a class, you can see the entire source code related to that specific class.
If you'd want to understand what it is all about, you can try and read the description which is present
at the top.
Also present is the list of the methods.
You can also type in Control O or Command O. Control O or command O will get you to the list of the methods
which are present in here. So,
you can see all the individual methods and if you want to look at a specific one, then you can say
okay, I would want to understand the sort method and you can see the syntax of it and also, you can see
the Java doc related to that.
These are long thing and you can read that it's related to a sort.
So, this is one of the ways,
right. So, if you'd want to directly type in something, you can directly type in Java.util.list
and go there. The other way is, let's say, I'd want to say List list = new ArrayList( ), right. So,
let's say, this is the code I am using and I press Control 1 or Command 1 to import the Arraylist
and Control 1 or Command 1 to import the List as well.
Once you do this, you can do a Control or Command and Click. So, Control or Command and Click. So, press
Control and Click or press Command and Click.
It would also take you to the same place.
Now I can look at all the documentation behind the ArrayList class as well. So,
this is the way you can explore API in Eclipse.
You can also look at the methods which are present by pressing Control O or Command O. If you want to understand
the type hierarchy of list, what are the implementation of the list, all that you need to do is say, right
click on the List and say Open Type Hierarchy. That shows the entire Type Hierarchy. So, you can see that
list interface is implemented by AbstractList, ArrayList, CopyOnWriteArrayList, and lot of other
stuff. You can see what are the different elements, methods, which are present in each of these classes
as well.
If you don't really want all the details, but you just want to have a Quick Type Hierarchy, you can say
right click and Quick Type Hierarchy and this would show the high-level overview of the type hierarchy of
that specific interface or the class. In this quick video, we wanted to give you an overview of how to
explore different APIs using Eclipse.
You can also get the same information by going to Google. All that you need to do is, go to Google and
type in the interface, list interface I would want to find out more about. So, Java list, I would want to
find the documentation related to Java 9. So, I put in jdk 9 and typed in Javadoc. Once you
go in here, you can go ahead and explore the different things related to the list interface. You can see
which module it is present, in which package it's present in. You can see all these super interfaces, sub
interfaces, all the implementing classes, and you can see the description, and also overview of the methods,
and the description of the methods which are present in here. I hope you had an interesting time in this
video. I'll see you in the next one. Until then, bye bye.