Welcome back.
In this section on reference types, we looked at what is the difference between a reference variable
and a primitive variable.
We looked at the different primitive types.
We looked at a few reference variables, how they are stored in memory, how they are initialized, and how
does assignment and equality work with them.
We also discussed a few reference types which are built-in in Java.
We talked in depth about the String class.
We discussed a couple of alternatives for it: StringBuilder and StringBuffer.
We also looked at a wide variety of puzzles which are related to String and we also discussed about
wrapper classes.
We discussed about the eight wrapper classes which are present in Java, which are exactly corresponding to
the eight primitive types.
We discussed why we need wrapper classes and also  a variety of methods which are present in the wrapper
classes as well.
And, at the end of this section, we looked at LocalDate, LocalDateTime, and LocalTime APIs. We looked
at different methods to get specific data from the date, to get generic data like leap year, or length of
the month, or length the year, and also we looked at different methods to compare with other dates as well
as to add a specific number of days, months, or years to a specific date.
This was one of the first sections where we tried to explore some of the inbuilt APIs in Java. Exploring
APIs can get a little boring at times, but it's very important to understand what you can do and what
you cannot do
and once you know what you can do, you can easily explore and try to find the right method to do that
specific thing.
I hope you had a interesting time in this section.
I'll see you in the next section.
Until then,
bye bye.